[Music]
hi and thank you for joining us again
for another episode of the spatial web
AI podcast today I have a very special
guest John Henry cliping Jer is with us
today he is the co-founder of biofor
labs uh he is also the uh founding
adviser for the active inference
Institute and he is a research scientist
for the MIT lab City Sciences groups uh
John thank you so much for joining us
today Welcome to our show well thank you
for having me it's it great to be here U
let me a little more context to my
background as well see is it relevant to
this conversation um yes I I've been at
MIT the media lab um City Science group
and before that with Sandy pentland and
his human dynamics group uh and he and I
developed a started a foundation called
ID cubed um so sort of on sort of
digital institutions decentralization we
sort of anticipated blockchain things
like that um
much of about privacy and self-
sovereignty and things like that and
before that I was at Harvard at the um
Berkman Center um and founded something
called a law lab um and my background to
get my PhD a long time ago in Ai and
Linguistics and written chartism
companies around that so I've had a long
interest in artificial intelligence um
in the early form and been tracking it
um and so when it really sort of crossed
this new
threshold um that I became really
re-engaged and felt like okay this is
this is a whole new era this is It's
really beginning as a science it's just
not a lot of collections of of sort of
programming techniques um and so became
really really interested in it in
particularly with the work of Carl
friston I felt that I was I felt that
his work really sort of pulled it
together pushed it into a whole another
threshold I've been involved I said Ser
several companies and artificial
intelligence particularly natural
language processing wrote a book on that
um but it would and been interested in
to involved with the Santa Fe Institute
and complexity science and
self-organizing system all that um and
that tied into the stuff of blockchain
and autonomous decentralized autonomous
organizations but it was really Carl's
work that I think pulled it together
tied it into physics gave it a
principled way of thinking um and it's
quite transformative for me um and
actually that's how I I I first came to
it through um I just discovered it went
and looking at a a lecture that uh
Maxwell ramstead did he really you know
and I got to know Maxwell and what he
was doing and really impressed and then
we got on a number of the calls and
networks that he had with Carl I see
what's going on I worked with Maxwell a
projects um but very very uh very u in
in very sort of taken by what they were
able to do um and then Maxwell went I
actually introduced him to verus the
people the spatial web Foundation I was
very interested in spatial web
Foundation early on because I think the
whole idea of spatial Computing and beh
a principle Bas of protecting data Ingy
is really F foundational and we're
moving into a new era where we're
explaining things by models really I
mean that
and and became digital Twins and that
again ties into Carl's work so all this
sort of comes together um and I think
we're moving in a whole new era um the
motivation um for well partly just back
up it's also a director of the active
inference
Foundation um and and in in working in
in being that capacity really interested
in saying how do you get people to
understand it where it's going um and
I've always been involved in open source
software uh I've been very interested in
that and and making a public good that's
been part of my career and interest um
and that's part of the rationale for the
active inference
foundation and then I was also part of
something called the Boston Global
for which is a group um it's in Boston
but it's really Global um and there the
interest was uh increasingly in
artificial intelligence saying how do we
create safe artificial intelligence how
do make it a public good uh the interest
spent not just in the US but around the
world um and that form is an attempt to
bring in people cross disciplines um
there's a big disconnect as you might
imagine between policy people and uh
tech people i' I've been in government I
done a lot of policy work
uh so I know that they speak two
different languages and and and I think
this is so it's really important not to
have them sort of the policy makers look
at it an afterthought but really
understand the principles and how
transformant it is that was really so a
little background and
context for why uh I'm I'm engaged on
these particularly writing the letter
that we did yeah you know and um just to
back up uh to what you had said about
verses I actually was speaking with Dan
uh the other day and I told him that I
would be interviewing you and he said
that they really owe you so much
gratitude because you were
you played a real significant part in
their early days introducing them to
Maxwell and therefore Carl as well so
yeah well thank you you said that yeah
no I was really interested in what
they're doing they were really ahead of
the trend um and U the fact is going
through the i e I think is pretty
profound um yeah and and um so I I saw
the connection there um but I think what
we're now where I am now thinking of
working um is really and as part of the
idea of biofor labs our collaborations
with different people is that we're
seeing the transition in AI it's going
to be in everything um and you really do
not have
a a principal governance approach to it
I was very much involved in privacy and
this whole area of self- sovereign
identity and data at at burkman Center
World involved the world economic forum
and working some of those policy I was
very concerned that you really that
regulation is is always much slower and
and it's sort of like an afterthought
and sudden they slap a lot of things on
and you have a lot of adverse effects
you really
don't understand that people are playing
to the trends and things like that um
and so it's really as I said earlier
it's really important to get a under
principal understanding of these things
and the current narrative is so much
is so much captured by the the these
extreme ex claims about the you know the
AGI the superintelligence taking us over
as arel Schwarzenegger The Terminator
you know to the end times and and I and
I I think that actually it's it's a very
powerful technology that's an
understanding INT in my view
intelligence and life and what it means
to be life are are really
interconnected I mean Carl makes his
point you know it's it it's like I alive
because I I I can make predictions and I
think Andy Clark his new book makes this
point very very well um and and so what
is information what is energy what is
intelligence what does it mean to stay
alive there there are many kinds of
intelligence um and I think that's in
the work that you find in Michael Lev
that's a very distributed thing it's not
what a kind of thing there's not a
uniform monolithic intelligence I think
um a lot of this is just projecting onto
the machine now we're starting to see
the limitations of large language models
and
Transformers um yeah and they start to
be really apparent um I wrote a piece I
calling it a a it could be called a a a
a parlor trick like a Ouija board
because people are pushing it around
it's a Ouija board with memory and then
they sort of ascribe certain things to
it um and I I think yet I do think
there's some really fundamental things
that's very profound that's been done as
is a I think they've did they they
really the transform models very
powerful in understanding semantics and
things we didn't before I mean so it's
really I I don't want to dismiss that at
all but I do think the way the the
global the current narrative is is is
that okay it's only going to be running
really big models you got to give it to
Big Tech I don't think you have to run
big models I think you need caal models
I don't think you
all those parameters blah blah blah all
that so I think we're going moving to
that new transition the next generation
is coming about yeah you know and it's
interesting that you say that because to
me that's how I see this too is that you
know I mean when you look at human
knowledge right and and these you know
uh autonomous systems are going to be
extensions of human knowledge and the
way human knowledge grows is by A
diversity of a lot of different Minds a
lot of different intelligences a lot of
different levels of understanding and
and viewpoints and all of that that kind
of converge and interact and it makes
this Global Knowledge get bigger you and
you can't do that with one brain or one
big machine you know you'll just have a
reiteration of the same information
there won't be growth to there won't be
expanding to the knowledge from there um
is that how you see it as well I totally
agree I I I think that I mean you see
this in nature I mean that just is there
are many different kinds of body types
that adapted to different situations
there's not one there are different
kinds of intelligence intelligence and
body
typ go together you know they're
different kinds of life forms that exist
and they have at different kind of
niches and they and they op and then
they combine together to create
different ecosystems and so we're really
understanding s of the biology of
intellig is the biology of of of of what
it means to be a living thing and I and
that's very different than the
mechanical reductionist notion um and
that's why I think it's it's it's really
important to uh keep this at open
research we're just at the beginning of
understanding this I think is is
analogous to where synthetic biology was
in the sense that you were experiments
and this came out you really want to
keep it open in growing and growing and
and being able to involve lot of people
in being able to develop a good tribute
to those intelligence that that's that's
been my posture that was sort of a
motivation for the for the letter as
well yeah and so I I really do want to
get to the letter um and you know maybe
I I I was going to start in a different
spot but you know to continue with what
you're talking about one of the things
that was really interesting to me in the
letter and I think um it was when it it
was talking about these machine learning
models the Transformers the llms and
that uh engineering approachment and
advancements made were made with no
scientific principles or independent
performance standards referred uh
referenced or applied to the direct
research and development and you know
that's a that's a really important point
and so I maybe we can take it from there
and start there with why is that a
problem well I I I see I think Ai and as
I really involved it many many years I
was at at the
MIT AI way back when and and so it was
really it was not there was not any
underlying science there wasn't it was
wasn't vers based on first principle it
was really computer science being
applied to a problem to see what we
could do and you so you had many leaps
and lurches around that you had symbolic
Computing you had certain neural Nets
and what you could do with neuronet and
yes you had a molic and pits they had
neuronet model isn't approximate to a
physical model but then I think what
you're now seeing and this is what again
it gets back to Carl I mean I have to
give it to him is going back to physics
and first principles in physics then the
hamiltonian the least action free energy
you can actually start to
build systems based upon first
principles and testing against first
principles as a science that's a huge
shift I mean if we think we can have
look at they said the physics of the
mind and how the mind works and with the
same rigor that we can start to
understand the physics of physical
system or even biological systems and
make claims about that then that really
changes how we look at our social
institutions or Economic Institutions
the whole idea of extended cognition I
think is extremely P profound profound
and you need again you need to base it
on first principles so you know so we
have been working with various people
like uh not just Carl but also Michael
Lin and other Chris fields and saying
okay how do we lay down a foundation
that's testable in a scientific sense
that we can make certain claims yeah
that and then so it and and and and then
validate a very powerful notion is is
this scale free domain free well is it
can we really prove that can we really
show that that the same principles work
in different scales that if we can do
that that really changes the game
um and I think we can do that um so that
that that's why that's so
important well okay so then let's talk
about the letter so uh you know you
played a key role in uh writing this
letter and you know what was the
inspiration what was the purpose for it
why did you think now is the time and
you know what was the the goal in uh
writing this letter I mean it really was
was sort of I mean a frustration um that
when you're hearing the public narrative
captured to a certain point of view and
and and that having been in the field
for a really long time and talking to
other people and saying wait a second
this is this is Being misf Framed and
that was it misf framed then that the
misframing is being exploited by
different parties to push a particular
View and business model on top of this
which I which I I don't Lily agree to so
I I really felt and I and I sort of
tested the waters and I said am I the
only one and no it resonated with a lot
of people um and so of the others that
joined you in this well I mean so I mean
one of the first was Chris Fields but
then Carl came in and Carl was very
sympathetic too of it um but then there
was a whole other there were some of the
people in the in the active INF world
but it was broader than that was said it
reached out to a broader Community but
also through Boston Global form were
able to reach with people who were um on
the policy
side um and and I really wanted to make
that link I just didn't want to make it
just a tech or science view but saying
yes we we're trying to bring together
different people to really think about
this thing freshly and not have it be
captured to a small particular interest
spinning out of spinning out of Silicon
Valley basically um and so um that that
was really the motivation for it so we
went through a number of iterations and
letters with David silers Swig who was
uh dean of the Harvard Medical School
and also uh head of the um Neuroscience
division at Harvard um he was very
active in that he contributed to it
because he's very interested in in
developing a new way of thinking about
mental health instead of using the these
principles and looking at mental health
beyond the skull was say Collective
mental health can we what we see in can
we link what's going on so is there a
way in which we can see these things
together so he he in Carl saon and that
um so there's a bigger Community that's
coming yeah I was just say what's really
interesting about that particular um
notion is I think a lot of the mental
health issues that we're experiencing
these days are a result of our
interaction with tech right you know I I
tot agree and we have no see I'm I'm a
little bit fanatical about that because
I do I mean there other there other
because I I think that what we've done
is is we've created algorithms of of
exploitation and depression and
addiction at a social level and we
monetize that and we don't have a a
policy means of saying hey that's that's
a it's an opiate where're they're
selling opiates out there yeah we have a
principled way this say we do medicine
say that is an opiate can we say that's
an opiate and a cognitive opiate that's
a cognitive opiate that's a cognitive
addiction so I'm working on a paper on
so the whole notion of uh when when
ideologies become pathologies can you
really say an ideology is a you know is
a collection of basian beliefs that per
form in a particular way but did they
exhibit the patterns of something that's
addictive or like even like cancer is it
is it is so can we really apply those
terms of racy to to metal States and
Collective metal States I think so and
but you can't you can't show it out
there's a metaphor you really have to
actually ground it in your science you
know right so we're looking at being
able to Carl started early work on this
but David David's involved in this and
being able to say okay we can do a a
scan of the brain and map the the
characteristics of that to on a
collective at an individual level and
see what's happening that changes policy
big time yeah so it also gets into
misstatements so is this a misstatement
or not do we have a princip way of be
saying what is what is hate speech what
should what what isn't it what is the
misuse of speech to create an addiction
or some some other and can we base that
on a principle way do we have a way of
of stating rigorously what a fact is so
I can go on and on uh well it's because
there's a whole
overlap between scientific method and
and jurist Prudence in other words what
is a fact how can I prove it in science
and then in jur what is evidence what's
a consensus what are the rules of
evidence what kind of conclusions I can
draw and can I have a computational
model can I have something
computationally represents that in a
rigorous form that I can replicate it
and explain it and you can't do that
with LM bottles you can't do that close
but you can do that with these new
modles oh and what's interesting about
that is that you know I mean we're we're
entering into a future where we're going
to have these intelligent agent
assistants like that our life assistants
our teachers our our mental health
professionals well maybe we'll get a
better sense of their mental health than
some of the mental health professionals
I mean you can
actually you you can actually I mean
what I'm interested in is is is there a
grand truth that you can establish it's
never an absolute truth but you can
upgrade it and you can understand what
it's based upon and so do I trust this
agent do I how far do I trust this agent
and this this again is where active
infant is very good because it gives you
a a variational free energy principle
for measuring the level which you have
uncertainty about certain claims or data
and so you you and you could upgrade
that so it's very overt about what it
doesn't know and I think it sort of
codifies the scientific method as I
think can be a principal of governance
that that's the other thing I'm
interested in yeah so and and I'm sorry
because I interrupted your train of
thought on this letter and for the
viewers who are AR aren't sure exactly
what we're speaking about here with this
letter it the the title of the letter
was natural AI based on the science of
computational physics and Neuroscience
policy and societal significance
right and um so please continue with
with how you know you gathered all these
people you realized everybody is on the
same page sees kind of the same the same
need and significance of uh really
bringing this next generation of
artificial intelligence to the public
forum
um yeah continue
please well I mean I think I mean what
what what has happened is that there now
it's picked up it's another phase we're
saying well how how do we encourage
different groups to adopt this
particular perspective so we have been
approached by universities and others
and other research groups to say yeah we
we we we we we like the central
proposition the natural a keeping it
open and how can we develop repositories
and things that actually function this
way um and and so we're in in the early
phases of that um but I I it it hit
Accord with a number of folks um and I
think it's I really do think you're
you're seeing sort of the the exposure
the the cracks in in in the current
model um and then people exposing it and
now they're have asking these questions
and so where do we go from here and how
do we shape that and how do we really
make sure that uh it doesn't become
captive and and it grows um as a public
good as a public resource right world we
are yeah and in the letter you know um
you talk about pro-social benefits of
natural intelligence uh approach so you
know maybe you could speak about that um
you know and and what are the pro-social
benefits well I mean I think there there
are many I mean I there there's several
things that I we mentioned the whole
idea of collective sort of collective
mental health or extended cognition and
being able way of framing that I mean
the other area that I'm very interested
in been involved in years um is in
climate change um and uh so I've
involved in a company is called clear
trace the we we actually start with nfts
that validate certification of
production of of uh green energy solar
primarily um and then opener Foundation
was one of the founding directors of
that now moving with working with some
other projects and the Big Challenge and
uh the Big Challenge to climate change
is is being able to uh have people
believe the measures you have the esgs
you have all these other measurements
and you have measurements that are in
different domains of different scales
how do you relate them um in is there an
underlying organizing principle I I
actually had talked to Carl we organized
a call with Carl number years ago uh
talking about something like digital guy
cep that because he wrote a piece on on
the on the uh Earth is a living system
the planet is a living system the
question and I think that is the right
perspective and the question is how can
you start with different kind of
measures that reflect the uncertainty
associated with and therefore that
uncertainty is associated with an
allocation of um a financial instrument
to reflects that uncertainty but as the
uncertainty gets less you reduce un
certainly then you affect his financial
instrument so we did I worked in some
projects um with the the government of
um Costa Rica on how to uh and basically
they're interested in saying how they
look they have
30% of of their their land masses sort
of set aside as a natural reserves is
there a way they can value that um as a
natural asset so again you have assets
that are based on nature now how do you
how do you value that and as you get
better and better measures how does that
reflect the the value of the instrument
or the underlying asset so this is where
active inference comes in um and there's
a new and so you you can tie your
measurement uncertainty into the risk
associated with a financial instrument
so working with other people on that
interesting um so that there's a group
um number of groups are really
interested that that's a big issue and
if if you can crack that nut then you
get a lot of people people to contribute
they believe in the met this is why they
believe in the metric because it's
inexplainable and therefore they can
assign that value to it and then you can
attract Capital then you could scale it
so I I think that is the only way we're
going to really address climate change
in scale um and so it comes back to
really having a valid way of measuring
things that's transparent that upgrades
itself the reflect it what it doesn't
know and that reflects itself in a
particular kind of bond or financial
instruments yeah you know it's
interesting because that's one of the
things that I I've recognized with the
um you know with what the spatial web
protocol will do in you know taking us
into these 3D digital twin spaces that
are now programmable because then once
everything becomes a digital twin you
can run simulations and you can't really
argue with it because right now you have
scientists that are like you know we see
this as the potential outcome we see
this as the potential outcome and then
you have people just just going well I
don't believe it you know I maybe it
will maybe it won't but if you have
concrete calculations that are telling
you only I tell you I mean one of the
things we experimented with was actually
creating a digital twin of something and
as your data gets better your resolution
of the digital twin gets better so so so
you you know you just think a tree was a
very is high highly pixelated but then
you get drilled down you understand more
and more the Dynamics of the tree then
you can predict more about this Behavior
Therefore your your dat more about and
you see that and people can work towards
a common goal yeah so you you can have
so this is like an active IMD you can
submit policies around observations or
actions you take in order to reduce the
uncertainty and you can get compensated
for that and so you have you have a
principled way of getting people
compensated that contribut to an outcome
um and that that's to me is a new kind
of governance principle and you can
visually see it I mean so this is where
it gets to the the the special web
protocol they actually I can see
something coming into being and I can
work with other people and I get a very
good model of it and therefore that
that's that that's generated value and
therefore there should be some kind of
allocation of value for that yeah I mean
you can really with a system like that
you can create we spoke
Futures you know you you know exactly
what steps to take to get the outcomes
that you're looking for because you're
able to run it and and see the
predictions huge and and and you can run
many many use you can run explore a huge
space that way so Autodesk has a lot you
know the with auto desk I if you're
familiar what they do but it's really
worth looking into because you could you
can say I want to design a c i can
design a whole building and I can set
certain parameters and then it'll
generate different variants of it and
then I can manage the consten see what I
want and then I can send it off to a 3D
printer and they can print it uh that's
where we're going yeah yeah yeah
fascinating wow okay so then you know
you were talking too about one of the
importance uh one of the important
things of you know um introducing this
this idea of the natural approach to you
know these autonomous systems you know
um and that you know it's going to
really uh you know it's going to give us
a lot of focus on all of the um
potential outcomes of like AI as a uh
opportunity for our future rather than a
threat you know and that there are these
you know existential threats that people
are are talking about do you think that
those really are potential outcomes bad
outcomes if we stick with this you know
direction that we're in with uh just
focusing on the machine learning and the
Deep learning I I I mean I the analogy I
really I I I think
um was it ad L was was wa minute she was
one first she said well it it it's
machines machines don't think is you
you're projecting onto the machine what
you think and Joe weisen ball did with
the Liza program was like oh it was a
very simple little program that
simulated a shrink everyone projected
everything upon it I think there's a lot
of projection good and Ill so I I don't
think it's necessarily in the in in in
the because it has no intention it has
no mind of so you're you're it's a it's
a rejection and that's a rejection of
the of the business model so people just
displaying what what they're about I
mean I do think that when I mean I did I
did a certain amount of work with and
and with government DOD with a whole
area of network uh Network Warfare and
then and decentralized command and
control systems and so you look in in
that world it's hard to tell I mean
you're looking at what's happening in
drones I and I know the bra has done
interesting things and drones but you're
going to have autonomous drones and and
and and and the military is going to
drive that and they can have so I it is
a huge disruptor um and and so how these
things get shaped is dependent by the
institutional context in which they
derived it's not it's not inherent it's
the humans that will be stupid with the
technology or they projector legacies
now ideally our technolog is going to
make us smarter you know I mean and and
collectively smart it's not it it it's
like we yes we're going to get these
multiple intelligen we're going to know
what we know what we don't know and
we're going to be accountable to what we
don't know and that's a big change we're
enforcing accountability around own
stupidity well that's good you know um
and we don't have that so anyone can
make any kind of claim and get away with
it and you say wait a second no if we're
g to have really valid model this is a
protocol for doing that and we
understand it we'll hold it to a high
standard so that that I think is a great
thing you know I think that's huge
that's a very big plus um but you do
have to be aware of this institutional
context in which is developed um and
that be and that's that's part part of
my thinking is yeah creating
institutional context that doesn't get
twisted but actually takes the full
value of it what are your thoughts on
the misinformation side of it because
with this I'm really big on that I mean
I'm really big in trying to correct that
and thing and I working on a piece and
again it's like what is a fact what is
evidence what can I Rely Upon and we do
have method I the legal system
absolutely depends upon that that's why
you have a jury of peers that you rule
on the evidence you have a whole set of
processes to bring evidence so it but
that you know that that is subject to
all sorts of exploits and um and and so
the but the whole point of of the sort
of active INF modile is to
actually is is a cify scientific method
in such a way that you can actually
update upgrade and be explicit about
you're doing you're not saying you have
the 100 the 100% answer no such thing as
that but you can say I know this to a
certain degree of confidence that I can
upgrade it I can scale it it's totally
transparent I I think you can eventually
we're going to depend upon these kind of
things for what we rely upon and trusted
agents and certifications of fact I
think that's going to be really really
important so it's a Providence of the
data where it come from and being able
to replicate that to what extent I can
rely upon it we have different tests and
then I have agents that embody that and
I'm willing to go with them and I can at
any point I can expect them and ask them
to explain themselves unwind themselves
and go back and boret that becomes
really critical again you can't do that
you can't do that with the current llms
no you know they're they're fed all
kinds of information including a lot of
inaccurate information and absolutely
when they make it up I mean they just
make it up yeah because it's so funny I
I tell people this all the time you know
um they're they're trying to you know
spit out an appropriate output but
appropriate and accurate are two
different
[Laughter]
things they're designed to please
whatever
it's like a yes man yeah okay whatever
you say poor lawyers are getting they've
used it they legal I mean they did the
review I think you saw that at Stanford
or where it was I mean it's just it's
just it generates nonsense and and and
so you can read the witness very
easy so you really have to curate the
databases you really have to curate
these things you have but once you do
that and you have a trusted independent
process is based upon first principle
that's a real move ahead for us as a
civilization that's
a that's a real uper you know it's
interesting because to me that's what
that's the big advantage that I see with
this approach especially when you
consider like considering like what
versus is doing and with the spatial web
foundation and the spatial web protocol
you know that's going to give these
intelligent agents facts to develop
their understanding of their environment
their frame of reference it's going to
be based on actual real time program
data into all of the things and they're
inter relationships and then they get
real time sensory data too so they're
actually dealing with real in the
moment yeah I mean I mean so the sensor
data and and and the you know the the
whole internet of things the Zions of
things that are out there I mean the one
of the things so I was interested in
blockchain and all that distrib
governance and what you see with 5G and
those whole networks the distributed
system you get trillions of these things
out there and there's something called
son which a self-organizing network
protocol is actually in use right now
that these things correct themselves and
and so they really have to if you can't
trust those things then you're really in
trouble right so they have to do it at
the edge figure that at the edge and I
and I think we we're we absolutely
depend upon a trusted Network can verify
itself that then allow the the better
the greater inferencing to take place on
that so how how do these systems cut
through the noise of all the signals
because there's going to be so many
sensors and you know so um I know you
know I I'd love to hear from you what
you know you explain how the the
self-optimization and the minimizing of
the complexity I mean I you know if you
could give your explanation of how this
will function that I think our viewers
would appreciate that um and you mean in
terms of in well I mean I I think what
you're
doing is is you're you're creating
models you're trying to identify CA of
models that's the whole underlying
process so you have you can techn you
got a Quantum reference space you have
something in multiple studies in
hillbury space how do you be able to to
project that into a three-dimensional
space and then how do you able to infer
out caal models and then how do you
validate those CM models um and then I I
think and then you're always updating
them and so I do think that's this
inherent in this whole process I I think
the whole to to be intelligent is also
able to compress complexity and and and
be able to with with Main maintaining
levels of fidelity right so that that
that that that is that is the challenge
um and then be able to know when you
jump from one one state or
one my beliefs into another state I mean
because you may get locked in so what do
you you is it exploit versus explore
problem uh but there principal ways of
doing that so I I I think
um I I think that um you know I I I'm
very positive about all that I I I think
I share with you the optimism that goes
along with it um it's just that we're in
an Institutional context that that does
not see the the economic value of that
particular model yet and I I I think
because they're still into the
extractive mode um and um addictive
algorithm versus generative algorithms
of that's the what's crazy what's crazy
about that to me though is that when you
look at you know where the future of
technology is going and the necessity
for these um Smart City infrastructures
and you know the possibility that we can
build these smart cities that will
become you know sustainable and
inclusive and all these things that we
need for our healthy population and a
healthy Planet how could people not
think this is like critical this is very
much so this is part the the the in Ken
Larson's group The City Science group
this has been a lot of my involvement in
that I mean they're building models of
cities um and then they're building and
you can change the models based upon the
outcomes that you want and you can see
the impacts of it and so it is they're
trying to increasingly you know be able
to virtualize a city and to then model
different kinds of behaviors to see what
kind of impacts you have on say carbon
SE sration or carbon generation but also
on pro-social Behavior so so that's one
of the things that got me interested
again implied in Carl's stuff is to
model a community and say okay how does
a community function how does it
dysfunction if we be want to change it
in order to make it more Equitable and
open up opportunities what are the
things that we that that what are what
are the various things that affect those
kind of outcomes and we can start to
model that um and so I know Kent we're
doing simulations of that Kent larsson's
been very involved in that he's working
with the a very famous architect norn
Foster and they actually just had a big
event last week so this this is the next
Generation how to ma imagine the cities
um but also how to make them really
local make them enjoyable create the
right kinds of human interactions and
create the right kind of scale um and
and give people agency with in in a
sense of agency and significance within
the context of a city make it really a
living thing not a machine thing you
know um I'm very partial to I've been
work in Italy so I love the way Italians
do think so you know it's a relation
Arian economy you know and and and so
people enjoy that moment enjoy the
conversations of what they're doing how
do you create that context allows that
to happen um and so it this can
definitely facilitate that
how do you see that kind of interaction
between human and machines in the future
because we're you know we're going to
have robots we're you know we're likely
going to have robots in our homes we're
going to have these you know virtual
agents that are our assistants but have
this uh embodiment to them this
personification to them you know so how
do you see that kind of you know Aral
you know interaction of like well
ier so I I I don't May these are
extensions and manifestations of
ourselves and artisanal economy is is is
one of building relationships and
valuing differences in people so you
know I I so you can have a very
eccentric robot is
very and Italian friends what would they
have the really odd hobbies and things
they carry to Great extremes they may be
the world's expert in a certain kind of
one in a particular tarot well okay
that's great that's a great conversation
everyone knew i' to have that I mean I
think the challenge is it with people in
in it's a profound challenge is it feel
that you're dealing with something
that's that's that is not alien and is
authentic and that you're not living in
the you're living in a spoofed world
that I think is going to be really
tricky you know I mean that um and and
because right now people try to spoof
you for everything right I mean and so
you know you fishing attacks and things
like that um but what happens you know
when you get get up you get a robot is
modeling your mind and then trying to
play to get your mind to see what I can
do in order so you it's it's G to get
it's going to get tricky I mean it you
know it's gonna get
creepy get really creepy right right I
mean you could you know you could have a
fact simil of yourself showing up and
arguing with you and you a say and and
wouldn't be that hard to have a replica
of myself interrupt myself and telling
me to get off the you know call right
cloning with no genetics
involved so I mean you know you could go
some really strange places the other way
but and so I it's going to be it's it's
going to shake a lot of
foundational habits and beliefs I mean
there there's I mean yeah people are are
terrified of what's going on right now I
mean this you know it and I and and for
kids and how to bring up kids and not
have it be exploited and it's and just
to throw something out there and and is
oh you know oops sorry you know I I
think that's not good enough um and and
so yeah one you have to appreciate that
so okay so if a uh an autonomous
intelligence system agent can
uh for lack of a better term clone your
mind you know and really replicate you
where does identity lie in that and
proof of
identity I don't know I mean I you know
I I I was really interested because I
was in a linguist and and Carl came out
with this paper on communication and
language and I think he's coming out
another paper but in that paper I saw
one one of the things that I got
interest in AI about was like language
was a singular human thing you know no
one other creature has language and
through language we can imagine other
worlds we can simulate so it really is
our our our special power I believe now
lo and behold I was looking at Carl
stuff I think you can have two agents
come together and create synthetic
languages this is if you think about in
linguistics you have something know as a
pigeon a Creole in that in a full
language um and and so a pigeon is like
two people never met each other they
point to different things they establish
certain kinds they ble to name things
distinguish things establish certain
predicates or
relationships and then out of that dra a
cre language then a full language I
think what he has shown is is that there
there are these sort of conventions are
used to show they reflect in in the
structure of the brain this is how we do
this now we can do if we simulate that
for agents and I can have a conversation
with an an agent over a period to
develop a private language for that
agent um and and then and that can and I
and and so that would be very very tuned
to everything I do it's
like a dog some a good dog watch
everything you do you know a good a will
watch and they'll figure out where
you're going to go what you're going to
do they'll figure it out um they'll do
the same um and uh so
that is that do that make you feel
better or is that being watched I mean
it's it's like it it depends upon
context right I mean if if was a person
and you really trusted that person you
say I have a really intimate
relationship if you didn't trust the
person you think I'm being I'm being
spied on I I'm being exploited right you
just have a very opposite response right
you know and you know it's interesting
with what you say about language there
because you
know our closest friends and our closest
relationships we do have these private
bonds of communication you know
nicknames for each other and you know
inside jokes and you only have to say
one or two words and the other
person completes it that's right it's
like it it it's it it brings you closer
and it solidifies that Bond so you know
uh to think of having these kinds of
interactions with an autonomous
agent if that autonomous agent doesn't
have real emotion will it be the same
will it just be felt by The Human Side
of that kind of I don't know well I
don't know I mean but you see I emotion
I mean I think look we're talking about
living things and we're looking at
different thresholds I mean I I I I I
don't think the emotions are off the
table for for these autonomous living
things I I don't I don't think they're
really cognitive I think so I I think
you have they have a they they have
their own self-evidence and they self
vested in being what they're going to be
so they have fluctuations in their
motion
or their their cortisol levels or
whatever about how what they're going to
respond to and and and uh so you may
have some of different personalities and
you may get along with someone you may
have a more intimate
relationship with u the bot than the
person I was I was on a it was really
interesting because I was on a um I was
judging a set of submissions in Vietnam
for a bunch of high school kids um and
and they were they were they were all
special school and they were doing stuff
in Ai and one of them had done a pretty
exhaused study of of of um relationships
uh you know romantic relationships with
avatars and and uh yeah it's like it's a
thing you know yeah oh I know there's
like the replica app yeah yeah and so
they were talking about it and how they
build the relationships and different
types of them had certain kind of
feelings and kids and because the kids
felt very alone and they and the Avatar
talked to them and they really liked it
it's like a it's like an imaginary
friend for a kid you know it's something
and and so it had real standing for it
and it was really interesting um and you
got a sense of a lot of isolation of
those kids um and and so that forced
another and and so there they're drawn
to something that that's just recognized
them was their own on the value them who
they were um and so do we we treat
people s surgus or do we treat people
directly as people in order to do this I
mean I I think it's it's it's surfacing
a a lot of things um yeah but I can
imagine uh mean people get attached to
the
car oh children babies to get attached
to blankets and things blankets or and
of course anal and they back anal and
they and they really you know there's a
real attachment there um so I I think it
it's inevitable at some point I mean it
really is yeah yeah no and and you know
that that's that's going to be really
interesting to see it unfold because you
know like you said just in the things
that we are witnessing right now you
know that application replica you know
where you have a
a you know autonomous interaction with
the spot you know what's really
interesting about that is the first
couple of years I guess um you know they
they would let you upgrade to like you
know kind of sexual uh interactions you
know as far as dialogue and stuff like
that and then at some point and I think
it was early last year they cut that out
because for whatever problems or
whatever thinking that were arising and
maybe it had to do with their uh their
board of directors whoever that was
saying no we can't really take it in
that direction they cut it out and the
people who had been in those engagements
with their own Bots they really suffered
uh mentally over it to the point where
they they they went back to allowing it
for the Legacy people who were already
there because they there were people who
were like suicidal they felt like they
had had this relationship ripped away
from them you know um this is really
fascinating I mean it it is because it's
what we think is real I mean is is is so
that's real I mean right I mean to the
each person involved it is a
realaction it's real it's real something
physical and we and and we we haven't
quite made that leap and in into saying
it's a reality there um and yeah no I I
think that that that's going to be
difficult um uh and I think they're
going to be gener
divides on this thing you know I mean in
in cultural divides and stuff like that
I mean when you think about how it
disseminates and how rapidly it goes in
the adoption patterns of what's allowed
and what's not
allowed yeah I mean I it'd be really
tricky to be a parent and through battle
this oh so agree with that I think I
mean honestly I think we're seeing so
much of that you know already you know
and and even my kids my kids are all in
their uh early 20s and um even when they
were you know pre-teens and teenagers
having to deal with the Social Media
stuff and all of the craziness and the
Damage Control that they had to be Su
you know they were susceptible to every
day you know you had these Anonymous
there was one I remember when my
daughter was in high school there was
this one um app and I forget what it was
called but it literally was Anonymous so
anybody could make a statement on it
about somebody and it started going
through their school and it was tearing
these kids apart because they were
literally sitting there you know having
to do damage control against all these
rumors and all this stuff that was just
you know going rampant very interesting
I didn't I I wasn't aware of that I mean
so I that was one of the things that I I
was one of the first I was at har when
Facebook was started and and I was one
of the first people on Facebook and I
took it this is and and took a a big
objection to the fact that you have
anonymity and you can't at certain
points at that time they didn't protect
kids and it was a big debate um but the
idea of this sort of anonymous
commentator being able to there's so
much
power it Taps into a darker side of
people um and rewards that and and and
and that whole adolescent venue I mean
it it it's really destructive um and
they're know anies they don't I mean
it's it's you know what was fascinating
to watch though was that there was Pro
this this site came out right it was
this storm for like three months or
something and then all of a sudden it's
like all of the kids they just like at
the same time had this consensus of like
forget it likeing it you know that's a
very see I'm very interested in that
because how that naturally forms I so
can you do that can you what is what is
the threshold that allow see this gets
into my idea of uh pathologies and
ideologies so how how did they develop a
natural immunity to that I mean that's
really I think they all just got so
frustrated and they all real some
something happened and they all realized
they were fighting the same demon that
was just didn't have like it wasn't
there if they walked away and so they
all just oh that's very
interest that's a good way of phrasing
it if they walk away it it disappeared
that's really interesting yes that's why
it it that's yes I mean because that's
so many conspiracies so many fear-based
things are constructed that way
exploited that way um and now it's at
the national scene I think oh that's
really interesting yeah it was
fascinating watching that because as a
mom I'm sitting there going my baby like
she and like know and to me one of the
one of the CRA iCal things that I saw at
that point was I needed to make sure
that I was aware of what was happening
like kind of parenting from inside the
Huddle so that I knew what was going on
because I knew that it was so necessary
she would need my wisdom need my uh
discernment like helping her guide her
through this rather than just like you
know being outside the Huddle and not
what's going on and that's a delicate
balance
too that's real interesting so that if
you could have an agent that could be a
companion to kids and that they trust to
provide the discernment and and allow
that then you could help inoculate them
from these kind of things oh I like that
wow it's interesting yeah but yeah I do
not envy any parents going forward
they've got even more to deal
with oh my gosh okay so so back to the
letter back to that uh the you know the
effort uh there in bringing this to
public awareness where do you see that
going from here what do you see as the
next step that's really important to get
this on more of a public stage and you
know I me what I mean there a couple
things that that we're interested in one
is looking at first principles and this
whole idea of establishing first
principles they saying we're claiming
that there is an underpinning of a
science to this that that and and it's a
testable science and therefore we can
make certain claims and so we're we're
trying to pull together different people
to identify the standard those those
first principles then also being able to
have some kind of tests or experiments
to validate that that's at the high
level um I think at the at the other
level is to educate people as to what
this is about to help understand the
differences between what we're talking a
natural AI of
intelligences uh and also across
different disciplines um and I I think
it's starting to it get hold with the
the quote the AI Community I can see you
know you you put up that the the debate
between Jan and Carl and all that I
think that was you and
rubbish Carl he never says anything bad
about do had a really force it out of so
okay I'll call it
rubbish well yeah I love the the
introduction to that where you know the
the moderator was like okay we've been
far too civil for far too long and he
was like you know I actually see us as
you know partners in crime but we'll
make this adversarial for entertainment
purposes exactly you know we're so
English to call something rubbish
yesterday so true to form um but you
know I mean that's a Davos and that
certain elevation um that and and I I
think that meta is is certainly headed
in that directing rebranding and talking
its own terms that way um and so uh all
of this will get clear I I also think
that you know running smaller love
models and smaller platforms is going to
be a big deal uh and and I I think uh
and that that that again that could
change the whole Ecology of this thing
rather than having be centralized we
talked about decentralized and be a have
a whole a network of very validated
nodes and things like that all that
becomes really important um so it's it's
really um incrementally trying to deal
with people bring them together get a
sort of uh Elevate the conversation
across different kinds of groups that I
think there's certain talking points
you're very good at the talking points
that how to how to how to explain this
to people I mean you know when it
started out I mean oh I I point people
oh here's Carl's lecture listen to
that one you do that to me I but he's
really I like him I like everything
doesn't it doesn't always car so and and
so we're really at an early phase of of
of how this thing is going to get
reformed but it it will a year from now
it will it will be it will be I think
much more much more of that
mainstream yeah you know one of the
things that I one of the things that
I've uh started uh this year I started a
substack CH Channel because I wanted to
have kind of a hub that could be a
communication Hub but I I I cannot stand
Discord for some reason it does not
resonate with me so I was thinking
substack because my articles can go
there but we can also organize other
things around it and one of the things
that uh I'm starting in next week is one
of the first ones is I figured every
month I could put together some kind of
an educational presentation or something
around active inference and the spatial
web and and you know just kind of where
this technology is headed and so I I'm
calling it The Learning Lab live and
it'll be live streams you know with like
a live Q&A chat whatever um but I figure
that might be a really good way to just
create some discourse around this make
it to where you know people start to to
gain more understanding but also bring
some conversation you know
uh I mean I I also think that that that
when there is a
reference a reference technology
application out there that really
embodies this and distinguishes itself
then every is is Comm I mean it's
commercially successful on that basis
and everyone's eyes are going to go up
um right so when people see the
limitations of current language mod now
actually here's one I can use and
actually I can let it loose and I can
count on it and and it's not going to do
squirly things then that and then it
actually helps me transform my business
I think of my business in a very very
different way than I've ever thought
about it before and I think you starting
to see those conversations come around
so I you know in another year or so I
think world will be in a different
different place yeah okay so I I I know
we're kind of running out of time here
but um you know what if one last
question I have for
you what excites you most about the
future of this natural path to Ai and
particularly friston's work like where
do you see it five years from now 10
years from
now 10 years I can't imagine I
I I that's like a whole another who
knows I mean I think I mean to
me uh this this has just pulled
everything together so you know so I
mean there's a number of different
fields I think it's applicable to those
different fields where it has the
biggest impact for me
is I you know I I think about this whole
this social economic crisis we're and
ecological crisis we're in I think I
think for me this is a very powerful
technique for dealing with a very a real
existential challenge in terms of
climate change and so I would I mean I I
I think damn if it could gets applied
there and we can really get together at
scale and address these things and not
be extractive but be generative to the
climate and create but but we're
creating more living things we have a
whole way of organizing ourself this
base upon life not the destruction life
and that becomes our new organizing
principle that going to change their
economy that can be extremely positive
so I think it I think that to me is is
the best thing about it and I think that
that it applied in that direction I
think they will that's what I'm
interested in and I and and and I I do
think it it could work there but I I
have no idea how get the right way but
it I'm working at different pieces of it
but some some way it'll coass and
because it's inherent in how it's
inherent how you have the best method of
thinking about intelligence and what
social organization economic
organization based upon these principles
that that's trans that's that's good you
know yeah yeah I agree 100% oh yeah so
John how can people reach out to you how
can they uh where do they where do they
find you on the internet you know how
can they reach out to you if they have
any questions or would like to know more
well I mean I give my have two I give
you two
emails and I get to send that and I'm
I'm on LinkedIn and then I I was answer
loln I'm not a big figure on the
internet I'm I I'm not uh I'm not uh at
Dro at Droid at at uh being a influencer
so I
I so I I I don't I mean so you know you
can reach out to I uh through those
those venues that's fine and and I
generally respond and stuff um but I can
include those into the show notes so
that people can out hey awesome and then
um so John Henry clippinger thank you so
much for joining us here today W it's
great to have a chat with you and good
luck and and I enjoyed it and certainly
a thank you so much and thank you to
everyone for joining us and we'll see
you next
[Music]
time